Inventory of the Fenimore Chatterton Papers, 1863-1977
University of Wyoming. American Heritage Center.
Fenimore Chatterton Papers
1863-1977
1904-1954
Chatterton, Fenimore, 1860-1958
00239
2.9 cubic ft. (3 boxes) + art + artifacts
University of Wyoming. American Heritage Center.
Fenimore Chatterton was a Wyoming state senator and governor and practiced law in Riverton, Wyoming. This collection contains correspondence from his various occupations, family photographs, and his autobiographical manuscript.
Biography of Fenimore Chatterton
Fenimore Chatterton was born in New York and came to Wyoming in 1878 to work as a sutler at Fort Steele. He later operated a general store in Saratoga, Wyoming, and was elected as a state senator in 1890 for Carbon and Niobrara counties. From 1891-1892 Chatterton attended the University of Michigan’s law school and from 1894-1898 he served as Carbon County attorney. In 1898 he was elected secretary of state and served as acting governor from April 1903 to January 1905 to fill the term of DeForest Richards, who died in office.
In 1906 he moved to Riverton, Wyoming, where he practiced law and was also involved in water development projects in Fremont County for the Wyoming Central Irrigation Company. He served on the Wyoming Public Service Commission from 1927-1933 and retired to Arvada, Colorado in 1937. He was married to Stella Wyland and they had two daughters, Eleanor and Constance.
Scope and Content
Collection contains correspondence; photographs of Chatterton and the Chatterton family, Theodore Roosevelt’s 1903 visit to Wyoming, and two panoramic photographs of Riverton, Wyoming; materials relating to the operation of the Saratoga Mineral Springs Company; the manuscript for Chatterton’s autobiography Yesterday’s Wyoming; maps and blueprints for water development projects; newspaper clippings, two engraving plates, certificates of election.
Access Restrictions
There are no access restrictions on the materials for research purposes, and the collection is open to the public.
Related Materials
Fenimore Chatterton Papers at the Wyoming State Archives.
Acquisition Information
Papers were received from Fenimore Chatterton, 1953; Constance Chatterton Spears, 1974; and the Eleanor Chatterton Kennedy estate, 1993.
Access Terms
Chatterton, Fenimore, 1860-1958, Yesterday’s Wyoming.; Wyoming. Governor (1903-1905: Chatterton).; Saratoga Mineral Springs Company.; Water resources development--Wyoming--Fremont County.; Riverton (Wyo.); Wyoming--Politics and government.; Wyoming--History--To 1889.; Wyoming--History--1890-1918.; Wyoming--History--1919-1945.; Wyoming--History--1946-.; Art.; Artifacts.; Maps.; Photographs.; Businessmen.; Politicians.
Agriculture and Natural Resources; Water and Water Rights; Business, Industry, Labor, and Commerce; Politics, Government, and Law; Politics and Politicians; Social Life and Customs; Wyoming
Container List
- Biographical Material (Box 1, Folder 1)
- Correspondence, 1914-1956 (Folder 2)
- Correspondence, Law Practice, 1932-1933 (Folder 3)
- Engraving Plates, 1904 (Folders 4-6)
- Legal Documents, 1887, no date (Folder 7)
- Correspondence, 1904-1925 (Folder 8)
- News Clippings, 1933-1977 (Folder 9)
- Photographs: Family, Theodore Roosevelt, Miscellaneous, 1903-1954 (Folders 10-13)
- Proclamation for Assumption of Governorship, 1903 (Folder 14)
- Saratoga Mineral Springs Company By-Laws, 1914 (Folder 15)
- U.S. War Department Certificate, no date (Folder 16)
- University of Michigan Class Day, 1892 (Folder 17)
- University of Wyoming Honorary Degree, 1954 (Folder 18)
- Fenimore Chatterton Will, 1953 (Folder 19)
- Chatterton Writings, no dates (Folder 20)
- Wyoming Public Service Commission, 1932 (Folder 21)
- Speech for Wyoming Shippers Advisory Board, 1933 (Box 2, Folder 1)
- Wyoming State Land Board, 1907 (Folder 2)
- Manuscript, Yesterday’s Wyoming, 1957 (Folders 3-5)
- Certificates, 1893-1927 (Box 3, Folder 1)
- Maps, 1931, no date (Folder 2)
- Miscellaneous, 1903, 1935 (Folder 3)
- Photographs, 1893-1927 (Folder 4)